<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
<title>My coding blog</title>
<link>http://koalacoder.com/cadasta-blog</link>
<description>A blog about my coding experience as an Outeachy intern at Cadasta.</description>
<managingEditor>laura@koalacoder.com (Laura Barluzzi)</managingEditor>
<webMaster>laura@koalacoder.com (Laura Barluzzi)</webMaster>
<ttl>40</ttl>
<atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/laura-barluzzi/cadasta-blog/master/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />

<item>
<title>My self-learning path to sofware development</title>
<pubDate>Fri, 12 May 2017 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>I started to self-learn back in July 2016. During the first five months (July-Nov), I used to follow the great MIT course <a href="https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/electrical-engineering-and-computer-science/6-00-introduction-to-computer-science-and-programming-fall-2008/">“Introduction to Computer Science and Programming”</a>. Alongside, I used to read the book <a href="https://learnpythonthehardway.org/book/">“Learn Python the Hard Way”</a> by <em>Zed A. Shaw</em>. Shaw’s book is practical and has about 50 exercises: in the last one you create a simple web-game.
After concluding both the book and the course, I decided to explore different ‘must-do’ languages. In November 2016 I joined the Free Code Camp community to learn basics about Javascript, HTML, CSS and web-development. At the end of January 2017 I obtained their <a href="https://www.freecodecamp.com/laura-barluzzi/front-end-certification">Front End Certification</a>. I highly recommend their front-end exercises and tutorials, I learnt a lot from them!
 In late February 2017, while starting a voting application as part of the back-end exercises, I received a notification from the <em>Freecodecamp Vancouver Facebook group</em>: someone posted about a job opening for the Outreachy summer internship program. Was I eligible? Yes. Was it doable for my level? Maybe. After a bit of thinking, I decided to give it a try. For the entire month of March I learned how to use Git and I contributed on the <a href="https://github.com/Cadasta/cadasta-platform">cadasta-platform</a> by fixing some issues. Understanding code written by other people and spread-out in hundreds of documents was not an easy task. I couldn’t have make it without the help of other developers who answered my questions...
...my hard-work and self-directive research paid off though – the Cadasta team chose me as their Outreachy 2017 summer intern! Keep up the hard work!</p>]]></description>
<category>Self-learning, Outreachy</category>
<link>http://koalacoder.com/cadasta-blog/#post_12may17msptsd</link>
<guid>http://koalacoder.com/cadasta-blog/#post_12may17msptsd</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Changing career empowered me</title>
<pubDate>Tue, 16 May 2017 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>I grew up in a small Alpine Italian city called Belluno. Since I was a teenager, I started volunteering at a local fairtrade shop and I became ‘famous’ among my peers for my dedication to social causes. Although I was studying accounting and programming (I know, funny), my interests in human rights and global justice brought me to pursue international development studies. For about 10 years, <em>my dream was to work for NGOs</em>, co-operatives and enterprises that promote social justice.
In November 2015 I obtained my Master and the job hunting phase in international development began. Over a period of 7-8 months I applied to a couple of hundreds of openings all over the world. I’d say I wrote <em>thousands</em> of lines in motivation letters and many pre-structured application forms. However, I received <em>only one answer: <em>a rejection</em></em>. What a bummer! In Vancouver at least I obtained an opportunity at the <em>British Columbia Council for International Development (BCCIC)</em>. Although the internship went great, their budget and hands were tied so they had to let me go.
It was in July 2016 that I realized two things: (1) I was <em>not really specialized</em> in anything; and (2) A <em>safe paid career was not going to happen</em> in international development. With a sour taste in my mouth, I convinced myself to purse a <em>plan B</em>. But was this a defeat? I actually then realized that defeat would have been to keep going based on a <a href="https://youarenotsosmart.com/2011/03/25/the-sunk-cost-fallacy/">sunk cost fallacy</a>.
As a consequnce, for 9-months I have been self-learning programming, and today I’m about to start an internship as a software developer at Cadasta. Cadasta enables people in developing countries to better protect and manage their land rights -- ironically, my plan B is enabling my plan A... life is funny, isn't it?</p>]]></description>
<category>Career</category>
<link>http://koalacoder.com/cadasta-blog/#post_16may17ccem</link>
<guid>http://koalacoder.com/cadasta-blog/#post_16may17ccem</guid>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>