<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
<title>My coding blog</title>
<link>http://koalacoder.com/cadasta-blog</link>
<description>A blog about my coding experience as an Outeachy intern at Cadasta.</description>
<managingEditor>laura@koalacoder.com (Laura Barluzzi)</managingEditor>
<webMaster>laura@koalacoder.com (Laura Barluzzi)</webMaster>
<ttl>40</ttl>
<atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/laura-barluzzi/cadasta-blog/master/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />

<item>
<title>My self-learning path to sofware development</title>
<pubDate>Fri, 12 May 2017 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>I started to self-learn back in July 2016. During the first five months (July-Nov), I used to follow the great MIT course <a href="https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/electrical-engineering-and-computer-science/6-00-introduction-to-computer-science-and-programming-fall-2008/">“Introduction to Computer Science and Programming”</a>. Alongside, I used to read the book <a href="https://learnpythonthehardway.org/book/">“Learn Python the Hard Way”</a> by <em>Zed A. Shaw</em>. Shaw’s book is practical and has about 50 exercises: in the last one you create a simple web-game.
After concluding both the book and the course, I decided to explore different ‘must-do’ languages. In November 2016 I joined the Free Code Camp community to learn basics about Javascript, HTML, CSS and web-development. At the end of January 2017 I obtained their <a href="https://www.freecodecamp.com/laura-barluzzi/front-end-certification">Front End Certification</a>. I highly recommend their front-end exercises and tutorials, I learnt a lot from them!
 In late February 2017, while starting a voting application as part of the back-end exercises, I received a notification from the <strong>Freecodecamp Vancouver Facebook group</strong>: someone posted about a job opening for the Outreachy summer internship program. Was I eligible? Yes. Was it doable for my level? Maybe. After a bit of thinking, I decided to give it a try. For the entire month of March I learned how to use Git and I contributed on the <a href="https://github.com/Cadasta/cadasta-platform">cadasta-platform</a> by fixing some issues. Understanding code written by other people and spread-out in hundreds of documents was not an easy task. I couldn’t have make it without the help of other developers who answered my questions...
...my hard-work and self-directive research paid off though – the Cadasta team chose me as their Outreachy 2017 summer intern! Keep up the hard work!</p>]]></description>
<category>Self-learning, Outreachy</category>
<link>http://koalacoder.com/cadasta-blog/#post_12may17msptsd</link>
<guid>http://koalacoder.com/cadasta-blog/#post_12may17msptsd</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Changing career empowered me</title>
<pubDate>Tue, 16 May 2017 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>I grew up in a small Alpine Italian city called Belluno. Since I was a teenager, I started volunteering at a local fairtrade shop and I became ‘famous’ among my peers for my dedication to social causes. Although I was studying accounting and programming (I know, funny), my interests in human rights and global justice brought me to pursue international development studies. For about 10 years, <em>my dream was to work for NGOs</em>, co-operatives and enterprises that promote social justice.
In November 2015 I obtained my Master and the job hunting phase in international development began. Over a period of 7-8 months I applied to a couple of hundreds of openings all over the world. I’d say I wrote <em>thousands</em> of lines in motivation letters and many pre-structured application forms. However, I received <em>only one answer: <em>a rejection</em></em>. What a bummer! In Vancouver at least I obtained an opportunity at the <em>British Columbia Council for International Development (BCCIC)</em>. Although the internship went great, their budget and hands were tied so they had to let me go.
It was in July 2016 that I realized two things: (1) I was <em>not really specialized</em> in anything; and (2) A <em>safe paid career was not going to happen</em> in international development. With a sour taste in my mouth, I convinced myself to purse a <em>plan B</em>. But was this a defeat? I actually then realized that defeat would have been to keep going based on a <a href="https://youarenotsosmart.com/2011/03/25/the-sunk-cost-fallacy/">sunk cost fallacy</a>.
As a consequnce, for 9-months I have been self-learning programming, and today I’m about to start an internship as a software developer at Cadasta. Cadasta enables people in developing countries to better protect and manage their land rights -- ironically, my plan B is enabling my plan A... life is funny, isn't it?</p>]]></description>
<category>Career</category>
<link>http://koalacoder.com/cadasta-blog/#post_16may17ccem</link>
<guid>http://koalacoder.com/cadasta-blog/#post_16may17ccem</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>My first weeks as an intern at Cadasta</title>
<pubDate>Fri, 16 Jun 2017 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>My first weeks as an Outreachy intern at <a href="https://github.com/Cadasta">Cadasta</a> have been incredible. As agreed with my mentors Chandra and Kate, my starting task was to enhance the user experience by adding the <strong>language option in the user account</strong>. The result of this work in available on <a href="https://github.com/Cadasta/cadasta-platform/pull/1569">this PR</a> on Github. As you can see, Cadasta uses Python with Django.
To achieve the goal, on my first day I made a detailed task-list, which you can see on the PR description section. Fortunately, thanks to the fact I have already contributed during the application process, the setting up of the environment and the Git Flow were already known to me. This meant I could quickly start with the tasks. I’m going to write the next paragraphs highlighting <em>challenges</em> and <strong>moments of pride</strong> for each chunk of work:</p>
<h2><strong>1. Handling a migration</strong></h2>
<h4><strong>Challenges</strong></h4>
<p>It was the first time I worked with migrations and I didn’t have a clear idea of what it required to do. Following some online tutorials, I just learned how to run commands such as <code>python manage.py makemigrations</code> and <code>python manage.py migrate</code>. At first I believed this was <em>all</em>. Though I encountered a problem and an unclear error appeared -- I was unable to figure it out on my own. After asking for help, I was told the error was linked probably to the version of Python (2.X instead of 3.X). After fixing this problem, later on I also discovered I had to add, commit and push a migration file to Git Hub in order to add the model change to the PR -- another information I didn’t know and I needed help from someone else in order to figure out.</p>
<h4><strong>Moments of pride</strong></h4>
<p>I didn’t have one to be honest. But in retrospect I acknowledge the importance of asking for help with detailed information and at the right time. I was unblocked very quickly with the help from other people.</p>
<h2><strong>2. Activating translation of language stored in the user model:</strong></h2>
<h4><strong>Challenges</strong></h4>
<p>One of the biggest challenges I faced was to find detailed information (and understand) the Django documentation over topics such as <strong>Internationalization</strong> and writing <strong>custom middlewares</strong>. Some specific questions on how to activate the language stored in the <code>user.language</code> field were not available (or very hard to find) neither in StackOverflow and other websites. Further, the <a href="https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/1.11/topics/http/middleware/">Django page on custom middlewares</a> was missing key information such as the fact that middlewares should <code>return None</code> if not a response.</p>
<h4><strong>Moments of pride</strong></h4>
<p>I was delighted when I saw it working at the end: in this tough process I learned a lot and I built for the first time a middleware and a test using the Python unittest module <a href="https://docs.python.org/3/library/unittest.mock-examples.html">Mock</a>.</p>
<h2><strong>3. Adding feature to the API</strong></h2>
<h4><strong>Challenges</strong></h4>
<p>Again the main major block of this task was the lack of detailed cases in the <a href="https://cadasta.github.io/api-docs/">Cadasta API Documentation</a>. One of the reviewers of my PR required this addition by just mentioning it, and unfortunately my mentors were not able to guide me and quickly address my questions on <strong>how to start</strong> with this. For an entire day I was blocked and I could not understand where to find <em>detailed</em> information. However, on my second day somebody from the dev team helped me a lot and I could finally figure out everything.</p>
<h4><strong>Moments of pride</strong></h4>
<p>Firstly, I used my experience to improve the existing documentation: I wrote a mock up with <strong>curl command examples</strong> for each section and I shared this document with people in charge of the documentation upgrade -- my initiative was highly appreciated! Secondly, I was proud of myself since I learned a lot: although I needed the initial help to start, I then figured out everything on my own by reading existing code and pages on the <a href="http://www.django-rest-framework.org/">Django Rest Framework</a>.</p>
<h2><strong>Summary</strong></h2>
<p>My start at Cadasta was incredible since I felt a lot the ownership for my work. Facing challenges such as learning new frameworks or understanding the documentation have ultimately been positive experiences -- this makes me feel more and more like a developer.I guess this is the <strong>magic</strong> of coding at the end of the day:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>There’ll be always challenges, therefore there’ll be always gratifications and chances to learn.</strong>
-- my own words :)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://github.com/Cadasta/cadasta-platform">Cadasta git hub repository</a></p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/Cadasta/cadasta-platform/pull/1569">My first PR</a></p>
<p><a href="http://koalacoder.com/">My koalacoder website</a></p>
<p><a href="http://koalacoder.com/cadasta-blog/">My blog</a></p>]]></description>
<category>Outreachy, Cadasta, Work</category>
<link>http://koalacoder.com/cadasta-blog/#post_16jun17mfwaaiac</link>
<guid>http://koalacoder.com/cadasta-blog/#post_16jun17mfwaaiac</guid>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>